Guide to the George Breitman Papers TAM.169
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
George Breitman Papers
1928-1986
TAM.169
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
33.5 linear feet (69 boxes)
George Breitman was born in Newark, New Jersey in 1916. After working in the Civilian Conservation Corps, and the Works Progress Administration, he joined the Trotskyist movement and became a founding member of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) in 1938. He edited The Militant and served in World War II. In the 1960s, Breitman assumed responsibility for the SWP's Pathfinder Press and edited Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1929-1940, and wrote Malcolm X Speaks(1965). The Papers contain biographical items, correspondence, articles, various materials pertaining to his political activities and to the history of U.S. and international Trotskyism. NOTE: This collection (except for the unprocessed Addendum) is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Breitman, George
Box 1-67
Provenance
Donated by Dorothea Breitman (widow of George), in 1992.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection (except for the unprocessed Addendum) is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
George Breitman (1916-1986) was born in a working-class neighborhood of Newark, New Jersey in 1916. After graduating from high school, Breitman found work in the Civilian Conservation Corps, and later in the Works Progress Administration. By 1935, he had joined the Trotskyist movement as a member of the Spartacus Youth League, and then as a member of the Workers Party. He also became a leading activist and officer in the New Jersey Workers Alliance, an organization of the unemployed.
Breitman was a founding member of the Socialist Workers Party in 1938. In 1941 he assumed editorship of the SWP's weekly paper, The Militant. Drafted and sent to France in 1943, he was able to establish contact with a number of European Trotskyists and to help in the rebuilding of the war-battered Fourth International. After his return to the United States, he was again editor of The Militant in the late 1940s and early 1950s. From the mid-1950s to the late 1960s, Breitman worked as a proofreader and was a member of the International Typographical Union. In this period he was also the leader of the Detroit branch of the SWP. With his wife Dorothea, and Frank and Sarah Lovell, he initiated the Friday Night Socialist Forum (later called the Militant Forum), a weekly series that attracted a broad range of activists from the labor, left, student and African-American movements. Through this period, Breitman used several pseudonyms, including Albert Parker, Philip Blake, Anthony Massini, John F. Petrone, and Chester Hofla. Returning to New York in the late 1960s, Breitman assumed responsibility for the SWP's Pathfinder Press and was best-known for editing the 14-volume Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1929-1940 (1969-1979), for his work on various collections of the writings of James P. Cannon, and for his pioneering work on Malcolm X, including his Malcolm X Speaks (1965). In the course of these activities Breitman corresponded with leading scholars and added to his already substantial collection of Trotskyist documentation.
In the late 1970s Breitman opposed the growing trend among the SWP leadership toward what he viewed as a politics focused on the Castroist leadership of the Cuban Communist Party. Among the hundreds expelled from the SWP in the early 1980s, he played a leading role (despite an accumulation of serious illnesses) in establishing the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, which sought to unify U.S. supporters of the Fourth International. Breitman died of a heart attack in 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, published and unpublished writings, files on various political organizations and activities, bibliographical materials relating to the history of socialism, communism, Trotskyism and other topics, and biographical materials. NOTE: This collection (except for the unprocessed Addendum) is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Series I. Biographical, arranged chronologically, contains an autobiographical sketch, memorabilia from the 1930s and from Breitman's WWII military service, and materials pertaining to several memorial services.
Series II. Correspondence, arranged chronologically, contains the bulk of Breitman's correspondence, and is principally concerned with his political activities as a member of the Socialist Workers Party and later the Fourth Internationalist Tendency. Principal and/or prominent correspondents include: Betsy Barnes, Pierre Broue, James Cannon, Eldridge Cleaver, Farrell Dobbs, Al Glotzer, Daniel Guerin, Joseph Hansen, Gerry Healy, James Kutcher, Walter Lippman, Frank Lovell, Vanessa Redgrave, Ed Shaw, Robert Williams, Murry Weiss, William Worthy. There is also some Breitman correspondence in series III, and throughout series IV.
Series III. Political Organizations & Activities, arranged chronologically, is divided into two subseries, subdivided as follows: A. Socialist Workers Party: 1. General records and activities, 2. Educational Activities, 3. Publications Committee, 4. FBI Files - General, 5. FBI Files - James Kutcher, and B. Other Trotskyist Organizations, arranged alphabetically, which contains files on U.S. organizations preceding the SWP, on the Fourth International, and on those organizations in which Breitman participated after his expulsion from the SWP.
This rich series contains proceedings, minutes, reports, memos, pre-convention and other discussion and position papers, including those representing minority and/or dissenting viewpoints, as well as some correspondence of Breitman and others, and FBI files. There is coverage of the SWP from its inception, although the greatest concentration of material is from the 1950s-60s and from 1982-85, the period leading up to, and immediately after Breitman's expulsion. For the Newark and Detroit clubs, there are minutes, typescripts of Breitman's talks and lectures, and documentation of Breitman's several runs for public office. Many files deal with views of the USSR, the Shachtman/Workers Party split, Pabloism, and the Cochranite split, including: "Toward Brass Tacks," by James Burnham, 1939; W. Roark (Trotsky) Letters re Opposition, 1940; "Shamefaced Defensism," by Dwight MacDonald, 1940; "Russian Theses," by E. R. Frank, 1948-49; "Pabloism revisited" by Peng, 1955; and an account of a (confidential) interview with Louis Adamic, 1950. Significant files on African Americans include: resolutions written by R. Kirk, 1953; "Why white radicals are incapable of understanding black nationalism," by R. Vernon, 1963; the SWP Black Fraction, 1967-68; and various Breitman lectures and resolutions. Files from the late 1970s - early 1980s document Breitman's political differences with the SWP line, his expulsion and the aftermath. The James Kutcher FBI files pertain to the case of this legless World War II veteran who in 1948 was dismissed from his job as a Veterans Administration clerk in Newark, NJ because of his SWP membership. The other FBI files document the Detroit Friday Night Forum, and the case of the SWP vs the U.S. Attorney General (1980s). (Note: the "Club Executive" is a national SWP committee).
The bulk of the non-SWP material is from the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, 1984-86. Earlier materials include an extensive file of Communist League of America minutes and other documents, 1929-32, Workers Party minutes/documents, and a history of the New Jersey Workers Alliance, 1935-39. The Socialist Party files focus on the period of the "French Turn" (1936-38), and include minutes of the Left Wing and the Appeal Association.
Series IV: Writings, is divided into eleven subseries: A. Writings, General; B. Party History; C. Malcolm X; D. African-Americans; E. James P. Cannon; F. Leon Trotsky; G. Carl Skoglund; H. Alan Wald correspondence; I. Louis Sinclair Correspondence; J. General Correspondence.; K. Writings by Others.
Breitman followed closely, and wrote extensively about Malcolm X and African-American struggles. Subseries B & C contain typescripts, including that of a proposed book, Racism in World War II, and The SWP and the Negro Question; a 1939 typescript by J. R. Johnson (aka C. L. R. James) "Preliminary notes on the Negro Question;" ephemera documenting the Black Liberation movements of the late 1950s - early 1970s, notably the Freedom Now Party; transcripts of numerous speeches, interviews and radio broadcasts by Malcolm X; correspondence, including Eldridge Cleaver (see also series I) and James Shabazz; and lists of relevant articles in Trotskyist periodicals.
Subseries D contains extensive Cannon correspondence, writings and interviews, and Breitman's correspondence re the editing and publication of Cannon's writings. Subseries E contains a selection of Trotsky correspondence and writings (most are photocopies of archival and published materials), including several letters by leading U.S. Trotskyists, sent from Prinkipo to their American comrades, one small file of Natalia Trotsky correspondence, another of Hansen-Trotsky correspondence, and Breitman's correspondence re his editing and publication of the works of Trotsky.
Breitman corresponded with Carl Skoglund, Minneapolis Trotskyist and Teamster leader, re what appears to have been a biography, and the files contain fragmentary portions of the unpublished typescript. Breitman also corresponded with historian Alan Wald, with Trotsky bibliographer Louis Sinclair and others, including Pierre Broue, Trotsky's grandson (four files covering the years 1972-1983). Breitman also accumulated a number of typescripts by other Trotskyists.
Series V. Lists and Indexes, contains general and special topic contents lists and indexes for the Trotskyist press, principally that of the SWP, and several lists of pseudonyms.
Arrangement
The Papers are organized into six series: I. Biographical Materials; II. Correspondence; III. Political Organizations and Activities; IV. Writings; V. Lists and Indexes; VI. Addendum (Unprocessed)
Folders are generally arranged chronologically within each series with some exceptions.
NOTE: This collection (except for the unprocessed Addendum) is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Frank Lovell Papers (Tamiment 204)
Separated Material
A small number of photographs (31 images) have been separated to the NonPrint collection.
The Breitman Audiotapes have been separated and accessioned as Sound Collection # 38. There are approximately 158 audiocassette and reel to reel recordings, c.1956 - c.1983, of various public programs (meetings, speeches, radio shows, etc.), organized into three series: I. Malcolm X & Other Personalities (55); II. Movement History (2); III. Unprocessed Programs (100). A preliminary inventory exists; consult the Tamiment Archivist for more information.
Barnes, Betsy; Breitman, George; Broue, Pierre; Cannon, James P. (James Patrick), 1890-1974.; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998.; Dobbs, Farrell; Fourth International.; Fourth Internationalist Tendency (Group).; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999.; Guerin, Daniel, 1904-; Hansen, Joseph; Healy, G.; Kutcher, James; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Lovell, Frank; Merit Publishers.; Pathfinder Press.; Redgrave, Vanessa, 1937-; Shaw, Ed; Socialist Party (U.S.).; Socialist Workers Party.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Weiss, Murry; Williams, Robert; Workers Party (1940-1949); Worthy, William, 1921-; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965; African American communists.; Civil rights and socialism |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Communism |z United States; Correspondence.; Government records.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorandums.; Minutes.; Proceedings.; Socialism |z United States.; Trotskyism |z United States.; Typescripts.
- Series I: Biographical
  - Civilian Conservation Corps, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Workers Alliance - Arrest of Breitman, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Workers Relief and WPA Union membership card, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - World War II - Army experiences: 1943 - c.1947, 1943-ca.1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Croix de Guerre avec etoile de bronze, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Autobiographical Sketch [3 pp], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: U.S. Dept. of Justice (FOIA), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Broadside: Breitman Memorial Service - Los Angeles, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: 1935 -1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: 1950 - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jan 29 - Nov 10, 1954, Jan 1954-Nov 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Nov 11 - Dec 31, 1954, Nov 1954-Dec 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: 1954 - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Feb 24, 1955, Jan 1955-Feb 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Mar 2 - Apr 26, 1955, Mar 1955-Apr 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: May 3 - Jul 28, 1955, May 1955-Jul 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Aug 1 - Dec 27, 1955, Aug 1955-Dec 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - Apr 29, 1956, Jan 1956-Apr 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: May 1 - Aug 28, 1956, May 1956-Aug 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Sep 4 - Dec 11, 1956, Sep 1956-Dec 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Sep 28, 1957, Jan 1957-Sep 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Oct 2 - Dec 31, 1957, Oct 1957-Dec 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Apr 29, 1958, Jan 1958-Apr 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: May 2 - Dec 31, 1958, May 1958-Dec 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Mar 28, 1959, Jan 1959-Mar 1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1 - Jun 22, 1959, Apr 1959-Jun 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jul 1 - Nov 27, 1959, Jul 1959-Nov 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Jan 19 - Jun 27, 1960, Jan 1960-Jun 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Jul 1 - Nov 30, 1960, Jul 1960-Nov 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Dec 8-28, 1960, Dec 1960-Dec 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4 - Aug 27, 1961, Jan 1961-Aug 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Sep 1 - Dec 6, 1961, Sep 1961-Dec 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4 - Jul 31, 1962, Jan 1962-Jul 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Aug 26 - Dec 31, 1962, Aug 1962-Dec 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - Mar 31, 1963, Jan 1963-Mar 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1- May 31, 1963, Apr 1963-May 1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jun 4 - Dec 12, 1963, Jun 1963-Dec 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - Mar 31, 1964, Jan 1964-Mar 1964 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1 - Jun 23, 1964, Apr 1964-Jun 1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Jul 12 - Dec 30, 1964, Jul 1964-Dec 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Mar 31, 1965, Jan 1965-Mar 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1 - May 27, 1965, Apr 1965-May 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jun 1 - Jul 31, 1965, Jun 1965-Jul 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Aug 1 - Oct 31, 1965, Aug 1965-Oct 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Nov 2 - Dec 31, 1965, Nov 1965-Dec 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Jun 29, 1966, Jan 1966-Jun 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jul 1 - Aug 31, 1966, Jul 1966-Aug 1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Sep 2 - Dec 30, 1966, Sep 1966-Dec 1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - Apr 27, 1967, Jan 1967-Apr 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: May 1 - Oct 31, 1967, May 1967-Oct 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Nov 3 - Dec 28, 1967, Nov 1967-Dec 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - Jul 28, 1968, Jan 1968-Jul 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Aug 3 - Nov 17, 1968, Aug 1968-Nov 1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Nov 17 - Dec 28, 1968, Nov 1968-Dec 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - May 2, 1969, Jan 1969-May 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: May 2 - Dec 31, 1969, May 1969-Dec 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - Jun 30, 1970, Jan 1970-Jun 1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Jul 7 - Dec 31, 1970, Jul 1970-Dec 1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - Jun 30, 1971, Jan 1971-Jun 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Jul 7 - Oct 17, 1971, Jul 1971-Oct 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence,: Oct 19 - Dec 31, 1971, Oct 1971-Dec 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1- Jul 16, 1972, Jan 1972-Jul 1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Jul 17 - Dec 27, 1972, Jul 1972-Dec 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3- Jun3 26, 1973, Jan 1973-Jun 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jul 9 - Dec 30, 1973, Jul 1973-Dec 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - Jun 27, 1974, Jan 1974-Jun 1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Jul 1 - Dec 30, 1974, Jul 1974-Dec 1974 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Jan 5 - Jun 30, 1975, Jan 1975-Jun 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Jul 2 - Dec 31, 1975, Jul 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - May 30, 1976, Jan 1973-May 1976 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Jun 3 - Dec 31, 1976, Jun 1976-Dec 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4 - Jun 30, 1977, Jan 1977-Jun 1977 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Jul 7 - Sep 20, 1977, Jul 1977-Sep 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Sep 21 - Dec 28, 1977, Sep 1977-Dec 1977 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4 - May 29, 1978, Jan 1978-May 1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Jun 1 - Dec 30, 1978, Jun 1978-Dec 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Oct 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Jun 28, 1979, Jan 1979-Jun 1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Jul 1 - Oct 30, 1979, Jul 1979-Oct 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Nov 4 - Dec 24, 1979, Nov 1979-Dec 1979 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4- Apr 28, 1980, Jan 1980-Apr 1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: May 4 - Sep 29, 1980, May 1980-Sep 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Oct 2 - Dec 29, 1980, Oct 1980-Dec 1980 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Jan 3 - Mar 29, 1981, Jan 1981-Mar 1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Apr 4 - Jul 12, 1981, Apr 1981-Jul 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jul 20 - Sep 29, 1981, Jul 1981-Sep 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Oct 1 - Dec 31, 1981, Oct 1981-Dec 1981 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Le Blanc, Paul, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 4.5)
  - Correspondence: Jan 1 - Mar 3, 1982, Jan 1982-Mar 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1 - Jul 28, 1982, Apr 1982-Jul 1982 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Aug 29 - Dec 25, 1982, Aug 1982-Dec 1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Jan 5 - Feb 27, 1983, Jan 1983-Feb 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mar 1 - Jun 30, 1983, Mar 1983-Jun 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jul 5 - Dec 31, 1983, Jul 1983-Dec 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Jan 5 - Apr 30, 1984, Jan 1984-Apr 1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: May 1 - Jun 30, 1984, May 1984-Jun 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Jul 2 - Aug 31, 1984, Jul 1984-Aug 1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Sep 1 - Oct 30, 1984, Sep 1984-Oct 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Nov 2 - Dec 31, 1984, Nov 1984-Dec 1984 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Jan 2 - Feb 28, 1985, Jan 1985-Feb 1985 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mar 3 - May 28, 1985, Mar 1985-May 1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Jun 1 - Jul 31, 1985, Jun 1985-Jul 1985 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Aug 2 - Oct 29, 1985, Aug 1985-Oct 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Nov 5 - Dec 31, 1985, Nov 1985-Dec 1985 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Oct 8 - Nov 17, 1985, Oct 1985-Nov 1985 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Le Blanc, Paul, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 6.5)
  - Correspondence: Jan 4 - Mar 23, 1986, Jan 1986-Mar 1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Apr 19 - Jun 30, 1986, Apr 1986-Jun 1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Apr 1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series III: Political Organizations and Activities
  - Subseries III:A: Socialist Workers Party
    - Subgroup 1 -- General
      - Brochure for anti-fascist rally in Yiddish, 1930s (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Convention (Founding), 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Melos Most ('Left-Wing Correspondence' / 'Appeal Left Wing'), 1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Minnesota farmer-Labor Party, draft thesis on, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - National Committee, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Nazi pogroms, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Political Committee, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "Workers Voice" (SWP Lenin Branch, Newark District), 1938 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - American fund for political prisoners, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Anti-war fund campaign, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Burnham, James - "Toward brass tacks", 1939 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Constitution (as amended by 2nd convention), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Convention (2nd, New York City), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - French Trotskyism, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Minutes of the Club Executive, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - National Committee, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Negro work, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Political Committee, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Resolutions, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Russian question, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - San Francisco Bay Area majority - statement of organization, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - Wright, John G. "Ideological captives of the bourgoisie", 1939 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - Breitman U.S. Senate campaign/Assembly campaign, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Constitution (amended at 3rd convention), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Convention (third), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Convention (fourth), 'Dec 1940 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Majority documents, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - National Committee, 'Sep 1940 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Opposition documents - anonymous, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Opposition documents - authored, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Opposition documents - "Shamefaced defensism" by Dwight MacDonald, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Trotsky memorial meeting - Chicago, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Roark, W. (Trotsky) letters re Opposition, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Breitman campaign for Newark City Commission, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - National Committee meeting, October 10-12, 1941; minutes, draft of revised declaration of principles (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Breitman campaign for U.S. Senate (New Jersey), 1941 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - Control Commission re: comrade Dennis (Flint, MI auto worker), May 1942 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Convention (10th) - New York City, Oct 1942 (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - Dobbs, Farrell (Labor Secretary) - letters to activists, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 20)
      - Goldman (?) untitled statement, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      - "Instructive experience in Negro work", Dec 1942 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Morrow, Felix: "From minutes of the National Education Department, 12/26/42" - includes 4 pp memo, "For workers' control of...shipment of...munitions to the...Soviet Union", 1942 (Box 14, Folder 23)
      - "The Jews and the Revolutionary Party", ca.1944 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Documents, 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Weiss, Murry "Notes for a discussion on the Negro Question", 1945 (Box 15, Folder 3)